hi everyone it's another Mastermind with
you is truly Professor Johanna Sophia of
johanna's raw foods and coaching
and the Rossum life project
so today is a topic that concerns many
of us and we all kind of have come to
the conclusion that okay
sweets are bad and we can't have them if
we want to be healthy and
there's so much about you know it causes
diabetes Etc and I'm gonna tell you a
story
that is different
um
but yeah let's get into it bit by bit so
this is The Mastermind the need for
sweet or the need for sweets you know
um I left out the S because it's just
about the sweetness really the need for
sweet
um
let us start with what is that
tweet
interesting is that in all languages
that I have come across in all cultures
that I have come across there's always
sweetness is also used as an expression
for something beautiful for something
that makes you happy for something that
is
um smooth and
easy on the eye or whatever it is in
French it's seduce
and um of course in Italian it's
the Sweet Life right
and so
I I'm not as good with with the African
languages that I did learn a little bit
off so but there too you know it's the
sweetest mango becomes the
the symbol for something that is
granting happiness or feels like you're
rich or accomplished or so sweetness
seems to me the world over throughout
humanity is associated with something
that creates a smile creates that
happiness
creates
connection
[Music]
um fulfilling it's something that
satisfies
so
when we called another person sweet or
we call that little animal oh look at
that sweet little animal right it's
always using the word sweet
now in terms of the biology what is that
what has us value this thing called
sweetness so much
as a human being
throughout the globe
so let's look a little bit at what
creates the sensation of sweet or what
does the sensation of sweet create in
our brain
and then we get to of course there's
certain taste buds that are The
receptors for sweetness and there's an
immediate connection to an endorphin
creation
so there's a chemical reaction in the
brain to to sweetness
put into your mouth right
and
how can that possibly be bad if it's the
world over
right
um
and then of course we look at
what happened historically
with sweetness over the last three four
hundred years and it's really only that
time
while we have had the grooming the
um
hybridization if you will natural
hybridization of fruits for example to
render apples bigger you know the
grafting method has been used by the old
Chinese for thousands and thousands of
years and I'm sure about other cultures
too that we just don't know enough about
um so that you take a branch from
a tree that happens to have bigger
apples than another one and you graph
that Branch onto the stem or a branch
off of a regular tree if you will or a
smaller apple tree and that apple tree
will also grow bigger apples so that
method goes way way back the selection
of the sweeter versions and then the
grafting the understanding how to
make more sweet fruit
and again because it goes thousands of
years back you know that the need for
sweet has always been there
because in our biology that endorphin
creation that smile on your face that
sensation is as old as Humanity
all right so we've had the hybridization
if you will by natural natural selection
by grafting etc for thousands of years
but then something happened 400 years
ago
when
the Europeans and yes it was just the
Europeans doing this
um sorry but it was this Cree I don't
you know I'm a I'm a
Global citizen
yes I found out about this because I
realized
um what your Europe has done to the rest
of the world over the last 400 years so
Europe went out in search of more first
more spices of course that the spice
trade goes back to the old Marco Polo
I'm spice trade all the way from Asian
countries into the Roman Empire and then
into the European
um Arenas but the new thing with
colonization especially with
colonization first of the Caribbean
islands
allowed the Europeans who could not grow
sugar cane in Europe people grew sugar
beets but they do not provide as much of
a clean
sugary liquid that you could crystallize
it's a much more complicated process
than processing sugarcane
so the sugarcane plantations
in the Caribbean islands were the first
to allow Europeans to increase their of
course going along with horrible
horrible enslavement and importing
slaves to grow the sugar
um
and then the bananas and of course the
bananas are also a very sweet fruit but
still the sugar cane is what was decided
in Europe would be
processed
by washing out and
boiling out all the nutrients that are
in sugarcane and sugarcane actually in
the wild is used as I learned living in
Africa is used to clean your teeth
because it does not do you any harm
eating natural sugar cane
so because it's very fibrous you break
the sugar cane you pick a fiber and you
clean in between your teeth with the
sugar cane you buy it on it on a little
bit of fiber you chew it you mull it
around in your mouth and it's very sweet
and delicious you can't swallow the
fibrous stuff but you then spit it back
out and it cleans your mouth and your
teeth
so
sugarcane however then was imported into
Europe and processed into this
White
sugar first into brownish sugar
and with the invention of colorism
with the invention of enslaving people
and justifying
the enslavement by way of a color scheme
a color scale
in human skin color this is an invention
and I want to make that super super
clear this is not anything natural
all humans are capable of the same
intelligence
Etc in fact of course many of the older
cultures of non-white or pale skin
um
had way more advanced cultures and
Technologies than Europe had at the time
so when the invention of white is might
and any other color darker would be down
the slope and at the bottom were
dark-skinned humans and the
justification of enslavement came along
with that the whiter the mightier
the whiter the miter
white is might was invented in the
European context actually
in collaboration with the church with
the Roman and other all other churches
and particularly the Catholic Church
suddenly had
ordered to burn all black Madonnas for
example all any kind of dark-skinned
representation of angels of Christ of or
Jesus of any kind of
Church Affiliated
um
artwork
in churches was to be banned
and this is something that very few
people know I just happen to meet a
scholar who studied intensively all the
documentation of that era and that's how
I've known for for decades that that is
indeed how it happened and suddenly food
also needs to be the wider the mightier
the whiter the better so the brown sugar
then the process was found to separate
the remaining molasses out of the brown
sugar and turn that into molasses used
for other purposes also sold as molasses
to have the crystallized sugar the
highly processed sugar as white as
possible
and that turns sweetness into guess what
poison
white sugar literally is poisonous to
the human body because our human biology
cannot break that white sugar molecule
down
in fact
and a biochemist explained this to me as
you take the color out of the white
out of the sugar molecule the non-white
sugar molecule the brown sugar molecule
still you have double bonds and the
double Bonds in the molecule allow the
body to break the atoms apart and use
the energy from the sugar
when you bleach the sugar
the double bond fuses and becomes single
Bond and now you cannot pull this
molecule apart anymore and what does our
body do
it either flushes it through
or it stores this none
digestible molecule in fat tissue
Now isn't that wonderful
so yes sugar does make you fat if it's
white processed sugar
on the other hand the original sugar
where you can pull those molecules apart
and use the energy
you can actually there with produce the
endorphins and an energetic flow today
we think it's the
it's the
glutamine
oh my God I don't want to say anything
wrong here let me just check it
um
that
that we need for all our energy
and I'm just looking
it up pulling it over here
so
oops come on
we can break that down
so we need the sucrose
and the
looking for something else
yeah and then they're talking about
sugar beets here versus sugar cane
um and sugar beets of course are still
grown in some places
but
the sugar cane became the accessible
sugar easily turned into white sugar
um when I was a kid we still had sugar
syrup from sugar Roots sugar beets that
was very thick very dark brown like
molasses but it wasn't molasses it was a
sugar beet syrup that we used like honey
on bread and bread and butter and syrup
you know literally that was one of the
Foods in in Germany and other countries
in Europe
so
what happened is the
denaturalization or the denaturing of
the natural sugar in foods that rendered
sugar toxic that rendered sugar
poisonous
right now
even if we are not used to eating fruits
anymore and of course in America many
many people are not used to eating
fruits but they have still the craving
for sweets so what will they do
grab a donut
grab it I mean it's not for not that
these stores are so incredibly
um incredibly profitable and everywhere
right the need for sweet remains in our
system as human beings and if we give
only the
poison sugar then the addiction gets
even worse to that poison sugar because
the body never gets out of that molecule
what it needs so the need just increases
increases increases and that's why
people eat cake every day and donuts for
breakfast and in France they eat
croissant every day with with some sugar
syrup every everywhere and of course
chocolates Etc now I can I can do
another whole Mastermind on cacao which
is also a food that we need because of
its high magnesium Etc
but we have again denatured and
modified it to an extent that it becomes
poisonous and it's roasted alkaline no
no um Alkali processed
um
form so
um back to Sweet
in the biology of nature
all plants
contain
sugars
to all kinds of varying degrees but as
I'm looking at the big
chestnut tree outside my window and I'm
thinking yeah
in the sack that goes up the tree and of
course maple syrup hello you know in
this step that moves up the tree to
fertilize the growth of the tree to
fertilize the leaves the branches Etc
is contained sugar and sugar is that
energy that drives the growth of plants
and sugar is that energy that all
creatures need yes even carnivores
needed a little bit of that too because
they too need to eat some grass and some
plant life like
um when I see our cat chewing and and
like licking and chewing on plant leaves
in my house or outside
I noticed something that
I hadn't really noticed before that on
many plants on each Leaf there's like a
tiny little droplet and that droplet not
from you watering it or something it's
like a tiny little droplet of sweet
sugary
thick
not quite sick but sticky liquid
um now I have not
done the research on that as I should to
see how many plants which plants have
that do that you know produce that
little bit of juice and I realized that
that is what my cat is
looking for
and
chewing with her of course carnivore
teeth into a little bit into the leaf
to get out some of that sappy sweetness
out of the leaf seems to be what even
the cat needs
so
all of biology has that Sugar element in
it that
we need
we being part of the biology of nature
right our bodies at least are
our mind is another thing that we'll
talk about
um
all of biology requires
that Sugar element
so
without getting into the details of what
sugar consists of we can understand that
and can realize that that is a truth on
planet Earth
therefore it also becomes then natural
that
diseases can actually be healed with
sweet fruit
now
um
many people you know when they first
realize that
they've become too overweight because
they've eaten too many sweets the
poisonous kind
then think okay I can't have bananas I
can't have mangoes I can't have you know
anything sweet apples
and in some institutions or some natural
practitioners also
have this the promotion or promote that
you should not have
sweet fruit only the
Savory fruit if you will right the
avocados the zucchinis the peppers the
eggplant those are all fruit
of course the nuts and seeds are the
nuts in particular are the the seed of
fruits right without the sweet flesh
around the fruit
um
think of an apricot because in the case
of an apricot we're used to eating the
sweet flesh but also the seed inside of
it which is like an almond is very the
flavor is very much like an almond and
of course it's the same family
um apricots and almonds so
what is it though
that we're missing when we're taking the
sweetness out of our diet
and of course I have tried this
because
um yeah because there's this this
opinion in my my teeth are really poor
and have been from from birth basically
from childhood and I I consider myself
lucky that I still have some of my own
you know at 70.
um
so yeah
we're worried about the deterioration of
our teeth due to sugar
but he is the other
little secret
I've already mentioned it
using sugarcane as it grows wild and I
happen to you know walk through
landscapes in Africa where sugar cane
does grow wild we were walking
in Malawi
um from the dirt road to this particular
um Lakeside Place
where hikers could could
stop and and live for you know like like
vacation
um
I can't remember we slept in a kind of a
cabin
and we ate the same dish every day it
was these little sardine-like fish that
were dried in the Sun and then cooked up
with the spices the little salts and and
of course
um what we called saza which is corn
Mash
and a big like Americans would call it a
coleslaw or something like a cabbage
salad
um
anyways so walking down the path to the
lake over 20 miles we really
walked for hours and hours and hours
um there was sugarcane growing by the
side of the road and to re-energize
ourselves we would stop and break some
sugar cane and chew it
and suck the sweet juice sugary juice
out of that sugar cane so I have that
direct experience of
experiencing the energy that you get
immediately from
fresh natural sugar and of course you
get that but you used to
considering it just food you get that
when you eat a mango when you eat an
apple or when you eat a ripe pear you
know you get that um
so good
and we
yeah in the western world today we don't
connect with that discrepancy between
the natural sweetness that energizes and
the denatured sweetness that
actually
anesthetizes makes you craving I was
going to say that kills but that's a
little drastic so because it just of
course makes you
unhappy in your body because it actually
also doesn't provide the happiness the
high if anything it creates a nervous
energy
um
you know that teachers describe when
when it's somebody's birthday and
everybody gets cupcakes and sweets in
the classroom and then everybody is
is jittery and everybody has ADHD for an
hour or two and then they go into a
slump and fall asleep at the desk
so
that's the poison
sugar effect versus the natural sugar
effect
just to
elaborate a little bit more on the
healing powers of natural sugars
I personally know several people and of
course
some have become very famous like Doug
Graham
and others
who have healed and helped heal many
many people
by giving them just sweet fruit for all
their nourishment requirements
now
I have always maintained that just sweet
fruit
is better when you also burn off that
extra energy by
um by having a Physically Active
life
Doug Graham typically works with
athletes right who who train five plus
hours a day
so that intense muscle workout burns the
excess sugar and
[Music]
the excess energy that you get by eating
a whole tray of 15 mangoes or whatever
you know which which fruitarians do
typically
but
even more astounding is that people have
healed themselves from diabetes on just
fruit
so the misunderstanding in my view is
that diabetes is created by
sweet sugar in Natural Foods
I say it is not it is create yes it is
worsened by the poisonous sugar but more
so than anything else it is created by
non herbivore foods that people consume
because they believe humans are
carnivores or omnivores
so the creation of Diabetes by
consumption of animal products
milk cheese yogurt
animal flesh you know all these products
that we call meat and Dairy
um
are of course
not for human consumption when you look
just strictly at the biology of the
human body
but sweets are
so sweetness
is part of a happy life
and even when people like you know Dr
Brian Clement who says you know no
sweetness after
or when you're trying to heal from
cancer because
all sweetness still feeds the cancer
that energy that you get from eating
sweets feeds the cancer cells more so
than non-sweet
foods of course all plant-based for
healing cancer and all raw for healing
cancer so
I agree that that is a good thing to use
especially in the case of cancer to have
low Sweetness in your plant-based raw
diet that is specifically for stopping
the cancer growth and having the body
eat up the cancerous
cells literally the body will discard
but also literally eat up the tumors
um
so I agree that sometimes it is wise to
lower the sugar intake but of course
even a sprout even a romaine lettuce
even a whatever the greens
even a zucchini Etc you know has sugars
in it and it can be sufficient for that
healing period but in my case now I'm a
very low
um
blood pressure
a little hole in my heart kind of
biology with all kinds of
um defects that's right that way you
know we all have defects but you know
some of us more than others and
I require that sugary energy I put
myself on a no sweet
fruit diet for two weeks once and I was
I could not run
I was out of breath all the time I
wanted to go to sleep all the time
of course you know I I did that at a
time where I was used to not needing
that much sleep in the first place now I
sleep more because I know that it is
helping my longevity plans to sleep more
and at the time I literally felt like my
energy level was like
I couldn't do it so reintroducing
sweet fruits and raisins and dates and
like I said mangoes and apples and pears
and strawberries and blueberries and all
those fruits that yes we have kind of
groomed to be
sweeter than they used to be a thousand
years ago
yet
if they are organically grown
and
relatively natural
they will provide that energy and that
endorphin power that we all need in our
body for a not just healthy but happy
life
so
um
healing with sweet fruit therefore can
also work now I'm going to show you a
couple of sweet things that I make
because I still think
um that it is the ultimate humanness is
creativity right is being creative and
making things now hopefully we're making
things that are enhancing those
biological processes not interfering
with those biological processes like the
denatured white sugar white rice white
flour you know white potatoes everything
you know that has happened with our food
because of that
switch in people's minds that white is
better Wonder Bread
you know I mean now most of us
understand that that is not a healthy
way to go
and still it is not really most of us
because
in terms of numbers the majority of
especially Americans but it can also be
said for for Western Europeans
um now even
even
Easter Europeans
um too
one more little anecdote when I taught
teachers and children in Romania in
when was that
1999 2000
um
it was just after
they had
eliminated if you will communism and
they had a pretty bad dictator chachesco
um and had westernized their lifestyle
it was
horrible to see
because of the economic
sudden
changeover
leaving most people totally impoverished
because if he couldn't have dollars
then
and where Euros already introduced I'm
just trying to think
yeah
um
you couldn't have the hard currencies
because
you had
so little if you didn't have Western
connection so when imperialism came into
the formally communist
world
it suddenly became
cheaper to buy two pounds of candy than
to buy a loaf of bread
or of
potatoes or you know two pounds of rice
maybe brown rice
um
yeah those were suddenly luxury items
and Candy literally two pounds of candy
you could have for pennies and children
were suddenly fed on candy and you saw
all the children in the city of
Bucharest bucharesti
um
with these rotten teeth you know two
Euros with their first teeth already
black and rotten
so that is how bad it can get
when the denatured sugar and of course
the children were craving more and more
of that sweet stuff right and the
mothers would buy these big bags of
pounds and pounds of sweets and feed
them to their children it was just
horrific to see
but they couldn't afford the potatoes
let alone the bananas
let alone any kind of fruit
even though Romania is a very very
fertile
country
and I actually drove through
you know it took a train through
all the way across Romania and saw all
the the
band and greenhouses and Fields Etc
because after communism
all the collectives
were disbanded and nobody was growing in
those areas and I'm sure corporations
took them over not shortly thereafter
but there it was you know years after
the supposed freedom
that imperialism brought
um all a lot of the land was
vacant and Abandoned and dilapidated and
there was nothing growing so that in
addition so
seeing how much damage
denatured sugar does to Children was
really devastating so
now
a short chapter about
sweetness as we perceive it
in terms of non-physical non-biological
sweetness
and why so many cultures have these
expressions of that was so sweet of you
thank you so much how sweet
oh isn't that sweet so the the
expression that something is sweet
brings with it exactly that same
endorphin project production in our
brain that renders us happy that
produces a smile on our faces
and
it should tell us
that sweetness is something very
valuable
very beautiful very much part of life
so instead of us saying oh
we shouldn't have so much sweets
of course we shouldn't have any of the
poison sweets none of it but we should
have more sweet fruit and sweet Roots
too carrots contain a lot of sweetness
sweet potatoes they're called sweet
potatoes because they're sweet right
um beets contain a lot of sweetness and
sugar
rutabaga and so much more
that we can
have more of and of course we get the
most out of the sweetness of plants in
which form
fresh from the plant just extract it all
right let's analyze
what I have here here I have a chocolate
mousse you know me and chocolate you
know I can't separate from that I don't
know what I'd do without raw cacao these
days
what's in here
that is keeping me energized and happy
in this particular moose I started it
off with the remainder of a green
smoothie
and a green smoothie in this case
contained a lot of red cabbage so it
wasn't really a red it was a red
smoothie but cabbage being the
cruciferous element that you know I have
often talked about
um
and then there was blueberries and apple
and banana and orange so
and there was a little bit of flax in
the Smoothie flax seeds so I started out
with this much smoothie in the blender
and then I added
organic raisins
now
I'm not sure how really raw raisins are
these days
but they don't give me the same feeling
I get from
um
from anything
cooked
and sweet so raisins
um often I put apricots but I recently
haven't had any I haven't found a
reasonably priced source for organic
um
apricots
see that smile on my face
so now in this is also
I was running on the walkway and there's
a lot of wild mint growing by the side
of the walkway where there's a little
stream
[Music]
and mint loves to grow in very watery
environments
and so I picked a bunch and I put it
right into the Vitamix with
where I was going to make the chocolate
with the raisins and the smoothie and
then I added
um
yeah I have a mix of other dried berries
I added a little bit of that
um I think this cranberries and
and also blueberries and
various berries in that mix
and then I added
virgin coconut oil about a heaped
tablespoon
and of course I made a whole blender
full right
and then I added a little squirt of
real organic vanilla essence
and a tiny pinch of salt
and a good cup full or a cup and a half
of in this case walnuts to give it the
body and the essential fatty acids
walnuts have a very similar profile in
terms of Omega-3s as do flax seeds now I
have a great source for organic walnuts
um
that I'm happy to share if you want
very inexpensive because walnuts in this
store can be outrageously expensive
here's another smoothie
I'll explain that one next okay and last
but not least
two heaping tables spoons or more of raw
cacao
and in order to break all that down you
need a temper stick and you probably
want to break down the raisins and the
fruit or the smoothie in there first
I may have also added some more fresh
blueberries which I often do
um
yeah and then then the walnuts and last
the raw cacao because that then thickens
it to an extent that the blender will
have a hard time
um getting through unless you have that
temper stick and
it's warm out it's in the 80s so it
becomes very soft as it moves but
then I freeze it
and it is gorgeous
just like that so it is
see that
into my little container and this is now
hard
there it is
um
and but it melts relatively quickly
because of the high fattiness the the
coconut fat and walnut fat
and you can make a whole blender full
and have it at your
desired time any time and keep it in the
freezer
all right now my daily fresh
smoothies
not every day I mean sometimes I do
something else sometimes I do Savory
smoothies I had a whole phase where I
was just craving Savory smoothies so
with with cucumber and celery and
kale and mixed greens and avocado and
then
you know squirt of mustard and salt and
a little tamari sauce and and cayenne
pepper
sometimes I put bell peppers also in the
mix or tomato so like a salad smoothie
Savory spicy was always with garlic and
ginger
in it as well so I had this whole phase
of where I wanted
where I was craving the
green Savory smoothies and I would still
have the the chocolate as well but yeah
this is a sweet smoothie and it is made
of
Orange
it is two oranges in this banana
Apple
and strawberries
and then a bunch of kale so half a
blender full of kale and then all these
fruits on top and
water
and because these fruits are relatively
mild the strawberries come through as a
flavor
really really delicious
and it has enough body to feel creamy in
the mouth
so again
sweet yet green is also possible
um I may have talked to you about my
colleague Dr Brooke goldner Who does
these very high cruciferous sweet
smoothies for all healing of
anything almost you know really it's
just but it works and again the
sweetness makes it easier for us to
consume and makes it easier for the
brain to get that kick up and go into
the oh we're
we're kicking it we're doing it we're
feeling great because that is what
sweetness does I mean I love spicy stuff
too so
when I make my spicy
salad smoothies often without water so
they're thick like a
like a spoonable pudding
um
even then I put either half an orange or
half an orange and a couple of pieces of
apple or pear into that mix to add
another little kick of sweetness to the
Savory dish
and it becomes the more exciting and of
course I also was introduced early
in my life as I began to to teach at
Columbia
um while doing my masters at the film
school I am
I had a private student
from east from India and he would invite
me and make these big spicy Masala fruit
salad for me
and
yeah loved that so it's another concept
of course that we're not so familiar
with in the west but sweet and spicy can
also be incredibly rewarding and
doing all the biochemistry that you
could want for that sense of
satisfaction and happiness
oh my God our time is up I've talked too
much
and unfortunately most of what I have
here is here's an energy ball
and that is coconut walnut
I don't think there's hazelnut in here
um
dates and raisins
and
raw cacao
again with a little squirt of vanilla
probably and a little salt so we have
these energy balls that are
so simple and outrageously delicious and
again provide that immediate
both sweetness and high energy because
of the Omega-3s and
are the good of course there's lots of
protein and all sweets as well
you know that's another issue people
think when you eat just fruits you don't
get any protein there's plenty of
protein in every single fruit on the
planet
so
that's wrapping it up
the need for sweet
is a real human need and should be
satisfied with the right
sweet fruits and vegetables from the
plant kingdom from everywhere on the
planet we have those even in the very
far north we have all these sweet
berries that grow very low to the ground
but they're wonderful
and they do the same thing that your
banana or your pineapple or your mango
does when you're in a more
Southern or in a more closer to the
Equator region you know whether it's on
the North or South hemisphere
all right guys
this has been your education for
sweetness so be sweet be your sweet self
find that sweet spot in yourself which
of course is another whole
area that we could talk about you know
why do we call it finding The Sweet Spot
and what is that that makes us feel
our sweet selves
in our confidence in our
being in our
uniquely special
Humanity
all right guys
I shall say goodbye
goodbye Shirley goodbye everybody who's
watching this at a later time I love you
guys do yourself the right sweetness
don't deprive yourselves
because life can be sweet
ciao